Guide to the Kenneth E. Bailey Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
Kenneth E. Bailey papers
1950-2016
RG 274
Yale University Divinity School Library
30
(64 boxes)
This collection documents the life and work of Kenneth E. Bailey, a renowned Presbyterian missionary in the Middle East, innovator in New Testament contextual studies, seminary professor, author, and international lecturer.
Bailey, Kenneth E.
Biographical / Historical
Kenneth Ewing Bailey was born November 24, 1930 in Bloomington, Illinois. The son of missionaries who served in Egypt, Sudan, and Ethiopia, Bailey learned Arabic and absorbed Arab culture at an early age. He studied philosophy at Monmouth College, graduating in 1952, and received an M.Div degree from Pittsburgh Theological Seminary in 1955. He and his wife Ethel began missionary work in Egypt in 1955, appointed by the United Presbyterian Church of North America to serve with the Egyptian Evangelical (Presbyterian) Church, first in village evangelism, literacy work, and Bible teaching, then at the Pre-theological Program of Cairo's Evangelical Seminary based in the southern city of Assiut.
When forced to leave Egypt for political reasons in 1965, Bailey moved to the Near East School of Theology (NEST) in Beirut, Lebanon and taught there until 1985. The Baileys went to the U.S. in 1970 where Kenneth enrolled in a doctoral program in New Testament at Concordia Theological Seminary in St. Louis, Missouri and also studied ancient Hebrew, Aramaic, and Syriac. Returning to the Near East School of Theology after receiving his D.Th degree in 1972, Bailey was appointed professor of New Testament in 1974 and was the founder and director of the Institute for Middle Eastern New Testament Studies, 1974-1984.
According to Gary M. Burge of Wheaton College, Bailey was an innovative New Testament scholar and "an ambassador of Arab culture to the West, explaining through his many books on the New Testament how the context of the Middle East shapes the world of the New Testament. He wed cultural anthropology to biblical exegesis and shaped the way scholars view the Gospels today." For more analysis of Bailey's contributions as a New Testament scholar, see Burge's article "Kenneth E. Bailey: An Ambassador Serving the Middle East and the West" in International Bulletin of Mission Research (2017, Volume 41, pp. 152-159.)
In 1985 Bailey joined the staff of the Tantur Ecumenical Institute near Jerusalem where he continued teaching and research until his retirement in 1995. He also served as Canon theologian of the Episcopal Diocese of Cyprus and the Gulf from 1990, and of the Diocese of Pittsburgh of the Episcopal Church from 1997. Bailey was visiting professor and lecturer at various institutions over the course of his career, including at Fuller Theological Seminary (1975-1976), Pittsburgh Theological Seminary (1985), McCormick Theological Seminary (1984-1990); the Theological College of the Greek Catholic Church, Beit-Sahour, West Bank, Israel (1988-1991), Dubuque Theological Seminary (1992), and at Columbia University and Princeton University. He was founder and director of Focus on Middle Eastern New Testament Studies (FoMENTS) from 2005 until his death.
Much in demand as a lecturer, Bailey wrote extensively, recorded many videos, and authored a musical play and a feature film in Arabic with English subscripts. Though a lifelong Presbyterian he was as well known among Anglicans and other Protestants as well as Roman Catholics. In addition to his work in New Testament studies, Bailey wrote extensively about his missionary vocation. His Presbyterian colleague and friend David Dawson has noted that Bailey wrote to "moderators of the Presbyterian General Assembly and staff leadership of the mission agencies about the 'integration' of missionary structures and the emerging churches during the second half of the twentieth century" and "particularly lamented the loss of long-term patterns of mission service that left missionaries without essential language capacity." (From Dawson's "The Significance of the Life and Ministry of Kenneth Ewing Bailey 1930-2016," a paper presented at the Yale-Edinburgh Group conference, 2017.)
Bailey died May 23, 2016 in New Wilmington, Pennsylvania.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the Bailey family, 2017.
Scope and Contents
The documentation of Kenneth E. Bailey's life and work available in this collection is extensive and complex. The papers have been sorted according to general format and subject matter, but the archivists have made no attempt to rearrange papers within the folders, choosing instead to leave the material essentially how Bailey had it in his own files. Dates and content types within folders and volumes are overlapping and not always relevant to their labels.
Series I, Bound Volumes of Personal Papers, contains twenty-nine volumes of papers that Bailey gathered and had bound together while he was living in the Middle East. Each volume contains a variety of types of documents and though the volumes are in general chronological order, there is no strict order within them. Bailey worked on organizing the volumes while in retirement, adding indexes and page numbers. The scope and content notes for these volumes in the finding aid were provided by Bailey's colleague David Dawson. These notes are not intended to be comprehensive but rather to give a sense of the topics and activities documented.
The Correspondence of Series II consists of documents received in folders and it dates primarily from after 1995 when Bailey retired in the U.S. There is also correspondence in the bound volumes of Series I. Notable correspondents include Lesslie Newbigin, N. T. Wright, Raymond Brown, Gary Burge, Markus Barth, George Carey, Sam and Eileen Moffett, Paul Pierson, Ralph Winter, Atef Gendy, Michael Nazir-Ali, Eugene Nida, Roland Bainton, James Dunn, Mary Mikael, Karl Barth, Richard Hays, Bruce Metzger, Jim Walther, David Hugh Kelsey, John Stott, Andrew Walls, Lamin Sanneh, Howard Marshall, and others. The series is divided into four subseries: a) Academic and with Publishers; b) Regarding Theological Education in the Middle East; c) General and Miscellaneous Correspondence, and d) Family Correspondence and Papers. The first three categories are overlapping and have been established only to give a general sense of the content of the correspondence. The contents of the folders in the General and Miscellaneous Correspondence subseries are overlapping in dates and topics; they have been maintained in the order received. According to David Dawson, Bailey had a type of dyslexia that affected his spelling and sense of organizational order. Much additional work could be done to index these files. Researchers who seek to decipher the files may find it helpful to read David Dawson's notes on the collection that are contained in box 56. These notes give a sense of the range and complexity of Bailey's files. The Family Correspondence and Papers subseries contains correspondence in general chronological order as well as biographical material, personal items, and memorabilia.
Series III, Biblical Scholarship Resources, is arranged by biblical book. The folders are ordered according to the labels that were on them; they contain a wide variety of types and dates of material. Series IV, Writings is divided into three subseries: a) Articles, sermons, and lectures; b) Miscellaneous writings and papers; c) Books. The folders in this series are as labeled when they were received; much work could be done to rationalize their order. Contained in the last box of the Articles, sermons, and lecture subseries (box 49) are printouts of articles by Bailey that were compiled by New Testament scholar Dale Bowne; these copies provide a comprehensive overview of Bailey's article length writings. Additional books by Bailey are available in the Library's cataloged collection.
Series IV, Audio-Visual/Digital Material, contains both computer files on floppy disks and DVDs. As time permits, the computer files will be preserved in another format. Transcriptions of audio and video files that were done by Dale Berne are available in box 62.
Arrangement
Series I: Bound Volumes of Personal Papers
Series II: Correspondence
Series III: Biblical Studies Resources
Series IV: Writings
Series V: Audio-Visual / Digital Material
Bailey, Kenneth E.; Bailey, Ethel J.
- Bound Volumes of Personal Papers, Series I
  Scope and Contents
  Documents in the bound volumes are often in reverse chronological order with a few older items from another period at the end of the volume. The labels of the volumes are as designated by Bailey.
  - Volume 1: Philosophy Notes (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Notes and papers from philosophy courses / seminars: philosophy of religion, ethics, ancient philosophy, modern philosophy, 19th century thought, political philosophy; senior paper: "Saint Augustine and Plato" (Monmouth)
  - Volume 2: Personal Lectures (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Miscellaneous lectures on a variety of topics: theology, bible, history of church, mission; farewell remarks to Near East School of Theology (Beirut 6/4/70); Presbyterian mission, "I Side with the Arabs" (1948); my priorities in the Middle East (clear statements re: the rich Middle East Christian heritage. "Recovering poetic structures in I Corinthians"; "Lucan Parables in Oriental Life"; thesis quotes [ThM at Concordia 1971-1972]; "Critique of Internationallization of Mission" (1972); "Proposed Foundation for a Theology for Mission of Presbyterian Involvement in the Middle East - last quester of the 20th century."
  - Volume 3: Seminary Notes (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Notes on theologians, history of doctrine, introduction to New Testament; seminary notes, papers for courses, notes from conferences attended including a Christian writers conference; Tarkio Institute of Theology.
  - Volume 4: Sermons (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Sermons – some manuscript, many hand written and typed outlines, some on recycled paper; some correspondence (1966 – just expelled from Egypt, awaiting visa for Lebanon) – includes 11-page paper on the cross in the Middle East – using a pen name; lecture on mission to Pittsburgh Presbytery (1966) that challenges the superiority assumptions of western culture and input of western missionaries; comment on western theologians who are irrelevant to non-western church – names several international theologians whom he commends…a reflection of missionary vocations; "Bread Upon the Water" – sermon on mission immediately following the Pittsburgh lecture
  - Sermons (II) (Box 3, Folder 1)
    Sermons – same type – seldom a date or place noted; lecture on John Chrysostom (pp. 306ff)
  - Volume 7B: Personal Papers (Box 3, Folder 2)
    1954 & 1963/64 (Egypt) 1967-70 (Beirut) Personal Papers – (1954 Egypt material after page 450…Fall 1954 missionary letters from Ewing Bailey) selection of new Executive Secretary of the Synod of Syria/Lebanon; some correspondence in Arabic; Egypt Mission Narrative Report (pp. 41ff); Addison Lietch letter from Gordon 6/23/69; appeal for Ken to spend time in US for "Crisis in the Nation Program" on racism (pp. 176ff); Ben Weir was COEMAR representative in Beirut
  - Personal Papers (VI) (Box 4, Folder 1)
    Personal Papers – includes 1968 letter ("One year has passed since we began service in Lebanon…"); correspondence from COEMAR (policy on designations 5/70) – notes from Ada Black, Secretary for Specific Program Interest, re: interpretation assignments in Iowa to presbyterials (women's associations); grades from Concordia (all "As") ThD to be awarded 7/28/72 – thesis: "A Study of Some Lucan Parables in the Light of Oriental Life and Poetic Style" noted in 7/6/72 letter re: their return to Beirut; list or museum pieces loaned to PTS 5+ pages; a dialogue on mission with 3 Middle Eastern churchmen; Gary Burge letter 12/12/74; Ada Black letter from I&S of Support Agency, she is Coordinator, Congregational Relationships in Mission; Institute for Middle Eastern New Testament Studies started at NEST – noted in 7/5/75 letter to Oscar McCloud; virtually all of this volume is correspondence, copies on onion skin paper or recycled paper.
  - Volume 8: Doctoral Notes N.T. (Box 4, Folder 2)
    Notes on courses on New Testament: the new hermeneutic, historical critical method, new quest for historical Jesus, N.T. eschatology and apocalyptic, early catholicism, form criticism, worship - speaking in tongues, gnosticism/Nag Hammadi, Qumran, Ephesians, missions, canonization of the N.T., Stephen, resurrection the N.T.
  - Volume 9: Doctoral Notes N.T. (Box 5, Folder 1)
    O.T. seminar, Ecclesiastes and Wisdom of Solomon, Apocalyptic, the indigenous church
  - Volume 10: Doctoral Notes N.T. (Box 5, Folder 2)
    Classics of Reformation, O.T. Poetry, Theology of Preaching
  - Volume 11: Doctoral Notes N.T. (Box 6, Folder 1)
    Kierkegaard and contemporary existentialism, Pastoral theology, Doctrine of Scripture, Doctrine of Salvation, Doctrine of God
  - Volume 12: Personal Papers (Box 6, Folder 2)
    Misc. correspondence w/ Index; Per. Papers; 3/28/67 (pp. 505ff) one-act play; personal reports: 1961-62 & 73-74; Reflections on Partnership in Mission (pp. 538ff); and other reflections as far back as 1955
  - Volume 13: Personal Papers (Box 7, Folder 1)
    Misc. correspondence; Personal Papers - also 7/22/66 letter to Westminster Press; 1965 letter; 1961 letters; 1966-67 letters; reflections; "Two Sons Have I Not" 1966 presented at Tarkio
  - Volume 16: Poetry Misc. (Box 7, Folder 2)
    Collected articles on poetry w/ table of contents
  - Volume 17: Personal Papers (Box 8, Folder 1)
    Misc. correspondence w/ Index; Personal Papers (also Vol. VII) – editing Poet and Peasant; Gary Burge letter 1/31/78 (p. 169-170); Gordon Bean 2/20/78 (p. 231) noted that the Poet and Peasant manuscript had been with the publisher 1 year when Ken wrote and found that they had forgotten that they had it…6 months later processed through their editors; letter to Sam and Eileen Moffett re: Presbyterian mission (10/17/78) p. 491-92
  - Volume 18: Lectures Heard (Box 8, Folder 2)
    Notes and transcripts of lectures by others - compiled while in Jerusalem, 1987; notes taken on scrap paper – Jonathan Kattub, Sam Moffett, Walter Bruggeman, Norman Horner, James Dunn, Paul Loffler, Moltmann, etc.,
  - Volume 19: NEST papers (Near East School of Theology) (Box 8, Folder 3)
    Correspondence, meeting minutes, reports; NEST papers and faculty/board and UPCUSA discussions
  - Volume 20: Personal Papers (Box 9, Folder 1)
    Misc. correspondence w/ Index; also vol. VIII; Personal Papers – academic correspondence; letters to Karl Barth on Middle East problem; James Dunn re: Poet and Peasant (pp. 66,74-79); Bruce Metzger; church correspondence; Gary Burge 12/17/78ff 3 more letters
  - Volume 21: Personal Papers (Box 10, Folder 1)
    Misc. correspondence w/ Index; Personal Papers (1966-1980) indexed letters, publications, manuscripts: Concordia Publishing [pp. 7-31 - thesis publication?]; "Functional Moratorium and Missionary Power" (49); "Who Is a 'World Christian'?" (p. 55); Eerdmans correspondence re: Through Peasant Eyes, 10/80ff (pp. 114-180); related/supporting church correspondence; family correspondence; personal reports; Marcus Barth re: Ephesians (p. 366); "Resurrection: Ode to a Burning Tank" (p. 372) and numerous essays
  - Volume 22: Personal Papers (Box 10, Folder 2)
    Misc. correspondence w/ Index; Personal Papers – indexed (461 pages in 2 years); Oscar McCloud – extensive response re: UPCUSA mission issues (pp. 245-250)
  - Volume 23: Personal Papers (Box 11, Folder 1)
    Misc. correspondence and collected articles w/ Index; Personal Papers (also vol. 12) – (1968-1981) – reflections on UPCUSA – NY staff coming for consultation and excluding missionaries (pp. 44-45); numerous reflection pieces; personal reports; [some duplicate copies from other volumes]; papers of other authors; reviews of Poet and Peasant (pp. 330-348); seems to have special interest in women in New Testament and church today
  - Volume 24: Personal Papers (Box 11, Folder 2)
    Misc. correspondence and NEST papers w/ Index; Personal Papers (also vol. 12, 1969-81) – indexed – NEST administrative documents & relocation – NEST newsletters; letters; essays; letter to Bill Miller on "Patterns of Service" [missionary categories] (pp. 194-96; personal reports; articles by others; letter to Len Rogers re: Gary Burge – 4/20/81 (p. 299); letter from Gary Burge 4/10/81 (pp. 312-13); Bethlehem birth story, c. 1981 (pp. 325-340); essay on 13th century Arabic writer's critical edition of the gospels (pp. 384-402); "The American Mission in Egypt…" autobiographical piece by Annette Bailey (Ken's mother); "Everyman" – Mediaeval Morality Play revised by Dr. Richard Graves – in which Ken acted
  - Volume 25:Personal Papers (Box 12, Folder 1)
    Misc. correspondence w/ Index; Personal Papers (1977-82) partial index – Middle East Evangelical Fellowship; letter to Eerdmans re: Through Peasant Eyes, 12/24/80 (pp. 26-27); reflections 5/6-7/82; telex from Verne Fletcher [NEST President for who a successor is being sought] that Ben Weir has informed Ken that he has been expelled from the Synod of Syria/Lebanon because he did not support the Synod candidate for the presidency [of NEST] - no date; misc. letters; issue of Rena Mussad's ordination (pp. 111-169)
  - Volume 26: Personal Papers (Box 12, Folder 2)
    Description of tourism sites and itinerary for visiting Jordan; misc. papers: NEST and articles by Bailey; a guide for Ken's [Mickey??] apparent first visit to Jerusalem – no date but pre-1967 because Jordon controls the Old City; reflections, including 6/4/79 re: NEST (pp. 63-99); reflections on mission in the Middle East (pp. 102ff); "When the Wind Is Right" (drama performed at NWMC) pp. 110ff; a study of Amos (pp.118 to end) dated 6/15/64
  - Volume 27: Personal Papers (Box 12, Folder 3)
    Misc. correspondence; Personal Papers (also vol. 14) – correspondence; 1/29/82 letter to Dr. James Walther [Pittsburgh Seminary NT professor] regarding and article which takes a different position than Ken's. Also notes that he will be the McClure Lecturer at Pittsburgh in 1984. Mentions reviews of Through Peasant Eyes and Poet and Peasant; letter from the Board of NEST re: the beginning of the search for a president to replace Fletcher 1/25/82…3/22/82 response from Ken
  - Volume 28: Personal Papers (Box 13, Folder 1)
    Collected articles and essays; lists 23 journal articles included in this volume (some notes related to the articles)
  - Volume 29: Institute for Middle Eastern New Testament Studies (Box 13, Folder 2)
    Papers of the institute w/ Index; New Testament Institute (also vol. 1) – index- The Institute for Middle Eastern New Testament Studies (at NEST) – budget, agenda, minutes, statement of purpose, correspondence. This would be a predecessor to what become FoMENTS post-1995 retirement. Microfilm of materials in the British Museum, Vatican, National Library of Paris, as well as Middle East monasteries, churches and private collections were acquired. Notes that Eerdmans is publishing his dissertation [Poet and Peasant] which will be out soon. "I am now calling my literary analysis 'Retorical [sic] Criticism'."
- Correspondence, Series II
  - Academic and with Publishers
    - Acorn Press, Ltd. (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - Arthur Meriwether Inc. (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - Blackstone Audio, Inc. (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - CRC Publications (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - Crossways International (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - Dar El-Thaqafa Printing Press (Box 14, Folder 6)
    - Harper One (Box 14, Folder 7)
    - Harper & Row (Box 14, Folder 8)
    - InterVarsity Press - Christmas Drama (Box 14, Folder 9)
    - InterVarsity Press - Correspondence with Editorial Directors; Miscellaneous (Box 14, Folder 10)
    - InterVarsity Press Handbook (Box 14, Folder 11)
    - InterVarsity Press 1 (Box 14, Folder 12)
    - InterVarsity Press 2 (Box 14, Folder 13)
    - InterVarsity Press 3 (Box 14, Folder 14)
    - InterVarsity Press 4 (Box 14, Folder 15)
    - InterVarsity Press 5 (Box 14, Folder 16)
    - InterVarsity Press 6 (Box 14, Folder 17)
    - Joan Armstrong, Essential Media Publications (Box 14, Folder 18)
    - Kregel Publications (Box 14, Folder 19)
    - Media Publications - Keith Brown (Box 14, Folder 20)
    - Newfield Publishers (Box 14, Folder 21)
    - Orbis Books (Box 14, Folder 22)
    - Scripture Union Publishing (Box 14, Folder 23)
    - Society for Promoting Christian Knowledge (Box 14, Folder 24)
    - Westminster John Knox Press 1 (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - Westminster John Knox Press 2 (Box 15, Folder 2)
    - Word (Box 15, Folder 3)
    - "Miscellaneous Publishing Correspondence" (Box 15, Folder 4)
    - Academic Correspondence & Misc. (Box 15, Folder 5)
    - Academic Correspondence (1) (Box 15, Folder 6)
    - Academic Correspondence (2) (Box 15, Folder 7)
    - Academic Correspondence (3) (Box 15, Folder 8)
  - Regarding Theological Education in the Middle East
    - "FoMents Special Reports" (Box 15, Folder 9)
      Christianity Today article on Roberta Green Ahmanson
    - "Endorsements of FoMents & Bailey's Scholarship" (Box 15, Folder 10)
    - "FoMents. Ibn al-Tayyib" (Box 15, Folder 11)
      Request: Thomas Schmidt on obtaining manuscripts of Ibn al-Tayyib
    - "Victor Makari" (Box 15, Folder 12)
    - "FoMents: Art - Arabic for I Cor. (Box 15, Folder 13)
    - "FoMents 2015-2016" (Box 15, Folder 14)
    - "FoMents 1997, 2000, 2001; NTSC Yearly Report" (Box 15, Folder 15)
    - "NTSC - Report 2002" (Box 15, Folder 16)
    - "NTSC - 2003 Original Report" (Box 15, Folder 17)
    - "NTSC 2004 Report" (Box 15, Folder 18)
    - "MENTS - Committee Meetings 2005" (Box 15, Folder 19)
    - "NTSC Yearly Report 2005-2006" (Box 15, Folder 20)
    - "NTSC Reports 2007" (Box 15, Folder 21)
    - "Committee Report Board 2008" (Box 15, Folder 22)
    - "FoMents 2009-2013" (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - Labeled" "FoMents 2009-2010 Committee Reports" (Box 16, Folder 2)
    - "FoMents Report 2012" (Box 16, Folder 3)
    - "FoMents Year Report June 2014" (Box 16, Folder 4)
    - "Pittsburgh Theological Seminary & FoMents" (Box 16, Folder 5)
    - "FoMents / General Correspondence" (Box 16, Folder 6)
    - "FoMents & Eastminster Presbyterian Church" (Box 16, Folder 7)
    - "Shenango Presbytery Appeal" (Box 16, Folder 8)
    - "New Testament Studies Committee Gifts/Thanks" (Box 16, Folder 9)
    - "Thanks for Gifts" (Box 16, Folder 10)
    - "FoMents: Presents / Gifts & Tapes" (Box 16, Folder 11)
    - "Thanks for Gifts" (Box 16, Folder 12)
    - "FoMents Fund Raising Documents" (Box 16, Folder 13)
    - "Fund Raising" (Box 16, Folder 14)
    - "Fund Raising 2004" (Box 16, Folder 15)
    - "Brochure - Fund Raiser" (Box 16, Folder 16)
    - "Sally Millison" (Box 16, Folder 17)
    - "Victor: FoMents Correspondence" (Box 16, Folder 18)
    - "Correspondence on International Editions of FoMents Books" (Box 16, Folder 19)
    - "Correspondence 'Fellows' & Miscellaneous Middle Eastern Scholars (Box 16, Folder 20)
    - "Kamal Forah" (Box 16, Folder 21)
    - "FoMents: Mike Parker" (Box 16, Folder 22)
    - "FoMents: Record of TV & Web Communication (Box 16, Folder 23)
    - "Letterhead FoMents" (Box 16, Folder 24)
    - "Correspondence Scholars / FoMents" (Box 16, Folder 25)
    - "FoMents & Overseas Center; Cairo Seminary" (Box 16, Folder 26)
    - "Cairo Seminary Pastors Course" (Box 16, Folder 27)
    - "Cairo Seminary Course" (Box 16, Folder 28)
    - "The Evangelical Theological Seminary in Cairo Communication" (Box 16, Folder 29)
    - "Cairo Seminary 2013" (Box 16, Folder 30)
    - "Quotes for Publicity" (Box 16, Folder 31)
    - "Web Recordings Refused" (Box 16, Folder 32)